To finish this section on if statements, we want
to look at two other aspects of if statements we
can use: nested ifs and compound conditional
expressions. This code example, 214-nested,
uses both to run through the logic of a game in
which players score points and collect coins. To
start, look at the variables declared on lines
one through three. We have a list of coins on
line one, a single coin within the list of coins
on line two, and then a score we will use to test
this code on line three. Before we go further,
here is a quick review question: Is the list on
line one immutable? The answer: no. Tuples are
immutable, meaning they cannot be edited without
being redefined completely. But lists are editable
and not immutable. Moving down to lines 5 through
9, we have an example of a nested if, which is an
if statement inside of an if statement. Why would
we need a nested if? If you have a condition
that leads to checking for another condition,
you have a need for a nested if. Let’s go through
this block of code line by line. On line 5,
we first check to see if a player’s score exceeds
10000. If that is true, the coins the player has
received determine which level the player is
on. The player needs a gold or platinum coin
to be on level 3. If not, the player is on level
2. None of the nested code is analyzed, though,
if the score does not exceed 10000. Sometimes,
you may not have a condition that begets another
condition to analyze with multiple possibilities.
Still, you may need two conditions to be true or
one of two conditions to be true for certain
code to run. Take a look at the example elif
statement on line 10. This statement is looking
for a score over 5000 and that the coin a player
possesses is within the list of coins on
line 1. If both those conditions are true,
the print statement on line 11 runs. If not,
the else part of this if-elif-else statement
runs the print statement on line 13. What do
you think the result will be in looking over
this code? Let’s run the code and find out.
We see that the print statement on line 11 is
printed. Part of learning programming is looking
at existing code, predicting what will run, then
running it and seeing if the result matches with
a prediction and why the result is the result. For
the code we have now, though the score is 10000,
it does not exceed 10000. Thus, the condition on
line 5 is false. Thus, we skip down to line 10;
the score is over 5000, and the coin is Bronze,
which is one of the coins in the coins list, so
this statement is true, and we see the current
results within the code. We have reached the end
of this section on the if statement, so it’s time
to do a practice analysis. This time, however,
you will need to discover one of the pieces to
the solution as it is something we have barely
mentioned. Take a look at this 214-analyze file.
Pay close attention to the variables on lines 2
and 3. The person testing this code expects to
see the print statement on line 7. However, when
we run this code, we see this result, which is not
even close to what we expect. Why? Use the Review
2.1 exercise in the workbook to discover the two
items in this code that need fixing and how to
fix them. Again, one of the fixes will require
your thinking outside a little of what you have
seen, and I would suggest maybe even taking this
code file and experimenting with it. In the
following video, we will reveal the answer.